Do you support the war against Ukraine? It is
поддерживаете ли вы войну против Украины
difficult to support war but you understand I will
Войну трудно поддерживать но понимаете я
tell you this:
вам скажу такую вещь
If Russia does not achieve its goal it may
Если Россия не добьётся своего она может
fall apart And if it falls apart this is what will
посыпаться А если она посыпется вот
happen This is what I am
получится вот то оч то чего я вот больше
most afraid of It is the
всего боюсь Это
disintegration into these small
вот распад на эти вот маленькие
principalities and endless slaughter
княжества и бесконечная резня
Hello Hello Where are you from
Здравствуйте Здравствуйте Вы откуда
I am from Moscow Got it I am from the city of
будете Я из Москвы Понял Я из города
Khmelnitsky This is your collection, excuse me The
Хмельницкий Это у вас коллекция извините
city of Khmelnitsky This is your collection of
Город Хмельницкий Это у вас коллекция
yellow pillows
жёлтых подушек
Yellow pillows yes Interesting Got it And these are
Жёлтые подушки да Интересно Понял А это
yellow I just collected them I had to put them
они жёлтые Я просто их собрал Тут надо
away Are they yellowed or
было убрать Это они пожелтевшие или
really yellow
реально жёлтые
Why are they yellow? I got it because I It is
Почему жёлтые А понял потому что я
strange I usually saw white pillows
Странно я обычно белые видел подушки
I thought that someone would shake them No, these are not
думал что их кто-то пожает Да не это
upholstery ones This is from a sofa A sofa Yes, I got it I got it
обивочные Это от дивана Диван ж А понял
And what are you talking about, young man
понял А чём общаетесь молодой человек
Well, with whom, how? In general, I just
А ну с кем как А вообще просто про войну
want to know about the war, how people feel about this
всё вот хочу узнать как люди к этому
matter
делу
I am far away In short, we are ordinary people, we do
отно я далеко Короче мы простые люди мы
not understand this Let the
в этом не понимаем Это пусть
politicians do this I talk about history About
политики Я я об истории общаюсь Об
history yes And you are a historian Yes, I am a historian by
истории да А вы историк Да я историк по
profession yes  I have 18 years of practice
профессии да У меня 18 лет практики
in 2 years I will have a twenty candidate of
через 2 года будет двадцаточка кандидат
historical sciences Yes The topic is Slavs on the
исторических наук Да Тема славяне на
territory of Rus' so I am just
территории Руси поэтому мне как раз
interested in it looks like where are you from, like
интересно выглядит Вы родом откуда как
your ancestors
бы ваши предки
Oh you know I was born in the
Ой вы знаете я вообще родился в
Rostov region and then well my father was a
Ростовской области а потом ну отец
military man there and then I myself was a military man I
военный там и потом сам военным был В
mainly served in the Caucasus Yeah And in what
основном служил на Кавказе Угу И в каких
years Well,
годах
starting from the seventies to the
Ну вот начиная с семидесятого по
ninety-second Yeah That's where I
девяносто второй Угу
served in the Caucasus
Вот на Кавказе там послужил
Where in the Caucasus did you serve in ninety-second
На Кавказе где В девяносто втором вы
This is Azerbaijan you know such a
служили Это Азербайджан знаете такой был
city was Kirovad and now Ganja Yes Ganja Have you
город Кировад а сейчас Ганджа Да Ганджа
heard No Yes
Слышали Нет Да
[music]
[музыка]
Nezami
Незами
Genjavi Genjavi yes That's how it is there pa
Генджави Генджави да Вот так там па
muzaley Ugu Haven't been there No, I haven't been Well I haven't been there
музалей его стоит Угу Не бывали там Нет
for a long time either I don't know
Ну я тоже давно там не был уже Не знаю
sometimes I want to go and see
так иногда хочется заехать посмотреть
what's going on there now And then it
что там сейчас творится А тогда
turns out you served in which airborne troops
получается вы вы служили в каких войсках
That is, you were there when the events took place in
То есть это вы были когда были события в
Sumgait and so on Yeah, not Sumgait, we wo
Сумгаите и так дальше Да не Сумгаит мы
n't touch
не трога
it  we were not attracted This is Nagorno-
это нас не привлекали Это вот Нагорный
Karabakh Georgia Then we
Карабах Грузия Потом
had to go to Yerevan Then
этот в Ереван приходилось е ездить Потом
when they smashed this border with
когда границу вот эту
[ __ ] they took out the families of
раздолбали сраном там вывозили семьи
border guards there Who smashed it
пограничников Кто раздолбал
Well local
Ну местные
Which families of border guards were singled out And what
Какие семьи пограничников выдели А какие
families are on the border The border there was a border
семьи пограничи Граница там же была
with this Iran Well on the border with
граница с этим с Ираном Ну на границе с
Iran there if I'm not mistaken there live
Ираном там если я не ошибаюсь там живут
Talash There is Linkaran
талаши Там это Линкарань
What-what is there the city of Lenkaran yes And there
Что-что там Ленкарань город да И там
Tala Talash or Talash live I don't
тала Талаши живут или талаши как А я
even know We flew there by helicopters
даже не знаю Мы на вертолётах туда
generally took and removed Yeah, I
залетели вообще забрали и убрали Ага
understand And in Karabakh what were you doing In
понял А в Карабахе что вы делали В
Karabakh Yes Lachin corridor Have you heard
Карабахе Да Лачинский коридор Слышали
No I have heard heard Well,
Нет Слышал слышал
when they had
Ну ну вот когда у них
[music]
[музыка]
there this is the road that
там это же это ну дорога которая
connected Armenia with this
соединяла Армению с этим с
Karabakh Well Well they tried to separate them but it
Карабахом Вот Ну пытались разнять но это
turned out even worse So there was nothing good there
получилось Так что ничего хорошего там
Our democrats have already started to
уже наши дермократы они начали уже так
set people against each other so much that God forbid
стравливать людей что не приведи господи
What kind of democrats have started  set people against each other
Какие демократы начали стравливать людей
Well, what kind of class Yeltsev just
Ну как какие которые клас Ельцев там как
arrived there Wait, do I
раз пришёл уже Подожди я правильно
understand correctly that Yeltsin set Armenians against
понимаю что Ельцин стравл армянца
Azerbaijanis and Iranians all this, yes Well,
азербайджанцами и иранцев всё это да Ну
it's not just him, but this is politics
это не только он а вот это политика
when it started And what kind of politics is it to
когда пошло А что за политика
separate Armenians from
разъединять это самое армян с
Azerbaijanis there And separate And they
азербайджанцами там А разъеди А они
lived in perfect harmony No, they didn't Well,
прямо душа в душа жили Да нет они не Ну
they lived normally The thing is that
они жили нормально Дело в том что потому
because they had common families
что и семьи были общие у них
Maybe maybe maybe maybe the problem is that maybe the
Може может может может может проблема в
problem is that the Soviet
том может проблема в том что советский
maybe the problem is that the Soviet Union
может проблема в том что Советский Союз
yes was for Armenia for Azerbaijan for
да был для Армении для Азербайджана для
Georgia for Ukraine Lithuania Latvia Estonia the
Грузии для Украины Литвы Латвии Эстонии
rest an occupation state And
остальных оккупационным государством А
why will he decide so That's how it was yes And
почему так решит Так так и было да А а
how did Azerbaijan become part of the
как Азербайджан попал в состав
Soviet Union Soviet Union yes
Советского Союза Советского Союза да
By inheritance from the tsarist empire No,
По наследству от царской империи Нет
when the tsarist empire collapsed
когда царская империя развалилась
Azerbaijan became independent Wait,
Азербайджан стал независимым Подождите
who annexed this part of
кто присоединил вот эту часть
Azerbaijan The main part of Azerbaijan,
Азербайджана Основная часть Азербайджана
by the way, is in Iran Yes South Azerbaijan
кстати она в Иране Да Южный Азербайджан
And there, if you count it that way Look again the
А там если так посчита Ещё раз смотри
tsarist empire collapsed and
эйская империя развалилась да появились
independent states appeared Georgia yes
независимые государства Грузия да
Armenia Azerbaijan yes and so on  further Who
Армения Азербайджан да и так дальше Кто
and how captured Azerbaijan that it became in the
и как захватил Азербайджан что он стал в
Soviet Union
Советском Союзе
Of course there were Bolsheviks themselves from
Конечно сами там были большевики из
Armenians from Azerbaijanism 26 Baku
армян из азербайджанства 26 бакинских
commissars subtracted No Once again Once again
комиссаров вычитали Нет Ещё раз Ещё раз
Look what local collaborators were
Смотри то что местные коллаборанты были
immediately immediately was what was organized yet Once again once again
сразу сразу была что организовано ещё
Russian troops
было Ещё раз ещё раз Российские войска
invaded Azerbaijan
вторгались в Азербайджан
What-what Russian troops invaded
Что-что Российские войска вторгались в
Azerbaijan No was Now let's
Азербайджан Нет был Сейчас
see So
посмотрим Так
here is the occupation of Azerbaijan 1920 On the
Вот оккупация Азербайджана 1920 год В
night yes 1920 1920 Here on the night from
ночь да 1920 год 1920 год Вот в ночь с
April 26 to 27 of the twentieth year units of the
26 на 27 апреля двадцатого года части
eleventh Red Army having crossed into the
одиннадцатой Красной армии перейдя на
territory of Azerbaijan from Khamcha from the
территорию Азербайджана с Хамча с
Yalomin direction entered Baku And
Яломинского направления вошли в Баку А
who was to make up this again the Red
кто был составить этой ещё раз Красная
Army is once again the Red Army is the
армия это ещё раз Красная армия - это
formation of what state was the
формирование какого государства было
Red Army
Красная армия
Yes there was no USSR then De RSFSR
Да не было тогда ещё СССР Де РСФСР
Russian twentieth year Russian still
российская двадцатый год российская ещё
such Russian was called a detachment still
такая российская называласьдерация ещё
gender No she And what was it called Now
пола Нет она А как она называлась Сейчас
I'll tell you Let's the Soviet Union when it
я тебе скажу Давай Советский Союз когда
appeared In the twenty-second year Well that's
появился В двадцать втором году Ну
right Nusr was Now we'll tell you how
правильно Нуср было Сейчас мы скажем как
it's called So yes so now now
она называется Так да
now What was it
так сейчас сейчас сейчас Как она
called Maybe now so
называлась Возможно сейчас так
Russian yes Soviet
вот Российская да Советская вот
Russian Socialist Federative
Российская Социалистическая Федеративная
Soviet Republic that's what it was called Since the
Советская Республика так называлась С
eighteenth year Since the eighteenth
восемнадцатого года С восемнадцатого
year yes Since 1918 it was called that Well
года да С 1918 она называлась так Что Ну
it occupied Azerbaijan in the twentieth
она оккупировала Азербайджан в двадцатом
year And who was in this army
году А в составе этой армии кто
Once again in this
находился Ещё раз в составе этой армии
multinational army it doesn't matter But this is the army of
многонациональной неважно Но это армия
which state This is the
какого
army of the state of Russia
государства Это армия государства Росси
yes Yes It captured Azerbaijan Who
да Да Она захватила Азербайджан Кто там
was in this army Even the Chinese
находился в этой армии Хоть китайцы
If they had captured it they captured or
Если бы они захватили это захватывали
rather if there was a population that didn't
вернее если бы там население которое не
want there
хотело бы там же
was also a massacre of some kind between the army then it
была резня ещё какая между армя то тогда
turns out look if if Germany
получается смотри если если Германия
captured who was the commissar there Wait
захватила кто там был комиссаром Подожди
if Germany captured Poland that means the
если Германия захватила Польшу то значит
population of Poland also wanted it I do
население Польши тоже так хотело
n't understand Well you say since they
Не понял Ну ты говоришь раз они
captured then the population wanted it that way
захватили то население так хотело
But it's a fact Look 1920 Russia
Но это факт Смотри 1920 год Россия
captured Azerbaijan Also in the same years it
захватила Азербайджан Также в те же года
captured Georgia
Грузию захватила
Georgia also captured yes Sochi Sochi it
Грузию тоже захватила да Сочи Сочи это
was the territory of Georgia Still Russia
была территория Грузии Ещё Россия
uh
ээ
captured there were no Bolsheviks
захватила не было большевиков
And what What were  There were and what were there Well of
И что Что были Были и что были Ну
course there were So they also headed
конечно были Так они же и возглавляли
all these So wait No look at
там все эти Так подожди Нет смотри вот
all this yes this
это всё да это это
this topic has been worked out We see how it
эта тема отработана Мы видим как это
works in the DPR LPR yes Some kind of these people
работает на ДНР ЛНР да Какие-то типа эти
appeal: "Lead the troops" And the
обращаются: "Ведите войска" И приходит
Red Army comes which introduces by
Красная армия которая вводит по ээ
conscription some ten local people
призыву какой-то десяти местных человек
Not only Russia So no need
Не только России Так что не надо
Russia captured It's a fact In the twentieth
Россия захватила Это факт В двадцатом
year, no one captured Azerbaijan
году Азербайджан году никто её не
Let's look again So the occupation of
Давай ещё раз смотреть Так оккупация
Azerbaijan
Азербайджана
And what were the British doing there So the
А англичане что там делали
British what are they doing there That's right So the
англичане что там делают Вот оку да Так
occupation of Azerbaijan on the sleeping military
оккупация Азербайджана на спаль военная
operation of units of the eleventh Red
операция частей одиннадцатой Красной
Army of the Vorsko-Caspian military
армии Ворско-Каспийской военной
flotilla That's
флотилии Вот
right I asked I wanted to find out you and
Да Я я спросил хотел вас узнать а
answer overthrew
отвечать свер свергнули
What were the British doing there The British did
Что там англичане делали Англичане там
not invade there If the British were
не вторгались Если там англичане были
present there they were doing there And what were they doing there
присутству они там делали А что они там
They were there legally at the
делали Они находились там легально по
invitation of the authorities Of whom Azerbaijan
приглашению властей Кого Азербайджана
And of which Azerbaijan
А какого какого Азербайджана
Government Well yes yes The
Правительства Правительство Ну да да
government was then headed what were
Правительство тогда возглавляли что там
those commissars there they simply shot at
эти были комиссары просто расстреляли по
No no  Look again In 1918
Нет нет Смотри ещё раз В 1918 году
Azerbaijan became independent
Азербайджан стал независимым
In 1920 Russia occupied it
В двадцатом году Россия его оккупировала
What's
Что не
wrong With Georgia the same thing yeah Yeah With
так С Грузией так же само да Угу С
other countries
другими странами
And Georgia didn't have its own Bolsheviks
И в Грузии тоже своих большевиков не
either
было Да что только русски были Не были
What's the difference The Russian
Какая разница Российская российская
army came to Georgia occupied
армия пришла в Грузию оккупировала
occupied
оккупировала
- after the revolution That's when the revolution
- после революции Вот когда революция
happened when they split then there were
свершилась когда они разделились тогда
Bolsheviks there were Mensheviks there it does
были большевики были меньшевики там
n't make any difference at all
вообще не по ещё какая разница
Bolsheviks and Mensheviks yes but they were
Большевики и меньшевики да но это были
on the territory No The Russian Empire all
на территории Нет Российская империя всё
this settled down and Soviet
это устаканилось и установила советская
power was established No look there were independent
власть Нет смотри были были независимые
states there Finland there Ukraine
государства там Финляндия там Украина
Poland stood at the head of Azerbaijan
Польша стоял во главе Азербайджана
Georgia Armenia Who were there Russians standing
Грузии Армении Кто там Русские стояли
or what No not Russians And who Well
что ли Нет не русские А кто
Azerbaijanis Well and then Russia
азербайджанцы Ну а потом Россия
occupied
оккупировала
Well after the occupation Yes after the occupation they
Ну после оккупации А да после оккупации
also sent Russian commissars
в том числе и русских комиссаров
Yes you remember that You
присылали Да вы же это помните Вы при
lived under the Soviet Union By the way not only
Советском Союзе жили Да кстати не только
look you Georgians but Georgians under Stalin
смотри вы грузи а грузины Сталина при
Once again You you you lived you  lived in the
Ещё раз ещё раз Вы вы жили вы жили в
Soviet Union You know look you
Советском Союзе Вы Вы знаете смотрите вы
know yes that there was such a policy yes
знаете да что была такая политика да
sent the same Yeltsin yes he was there there was
присыла тот же самый Ельцин да он был
cooler they were transferred to all
там там круче их перекидывали по всех
these republics in Asia as
этих там республиках в Азию как
commissars yes all this was yes
комиссаров да всё это было да
party chiefs yes they were put there
начальников партийных да ставили туда
So no need to tell it was an
Так что не надо рассказывать это была
occupation Well damn everyone knows all this they write all this
оккупация Ну блин все это знают все это
officially and you Russians are in denial
официально пишут а вы русские отрицатель
Why are you embarrassed that uh the RSFSR was an
Почему вы стесняетесь что ээ РСФСР был
occupier It wasn't you who occupied
оккупантом Это же не вы оккупировали
Azerbaijan though it's some kind of Why are
правда Азербайджан это какой-то Почему
you afraid of this What are you embarrassed about
ты боишься за это Чего ты стесняешься
[music]
[музыка]
So it turns out that the Russians have always been
Так получается что русские всё время
occupiers or something it turns out in your opinion
оккупантами что ли получается по-вашему
You come to the right
Ты правильно приходишь к
conclusion At one
выводу
time look at one time look at one
В своё время смотри в своё время смотри
time different empires developed The
в своё время развивались разные империи
British Empire it was an occupier
Британская империя она была оккупантом
for half the world yes The Spanish Crown yes it
для половины мира да Испанская корона да
was an occupier for there South America
была оккупантом для там Южной Америки
there all yes part of it yes yes The
там всей да части этой да да да
Ottoman Empire was an occupier yes That
Османская империя была оккупантом да То
is, in essence  there was a consolidation of powers
есть по сути шло укрупнение держав
because transport was developing,
потому что развивался транспорт
technologies were developing, yes, conditionally, the army
развивались технологии да условно армию
there, uh, it was easier to transfer, it was easier to
там ээ легче было переводить легче
control these territories, there was communication,
контролировать эти территории были связь
yes, and so they were consolidating, yes
появлялась да вот и они укрупнялись да
Then the so-called spring of nations took place at the end of the 10th
Потом прошла так называемая в конце X
century. Many
столетия весна народов Многие
began to gain independence. The First
начали независимость получать Первая
World War destroyed the
мировая война разрушила
Austro-Hungarian Empire, the Ottoman
австро-венгерскую империю османскую
Empire,
империю
and this Russian Empire. Yes, the Second
и эту российскую империю Да Вторая
World War destroyed both the British Empire, this Russian, German, not Austria, the Austro-Hungarian and Ottoman Empires, the Austro-Hungarian Empire, and what other empire? And the Ottoman Empire, the Ottoman Empire. Well, yes, the Ottoman Empire. Yes, yes. Not on the territory of the Ottoman Empire remained. The Second World War had already
оставалась Вторая мировая война это уже
collapsed, the British Empire, in fact, and the
рухнула британская империя по сути да и
French, French, various colonies,
французские французские разные колонии
like in Africa, and so on, yes, in fact. Well, yes, they, by the way,
типа в Африке и так дальше да по сути Ну
still have this
это да они они кстати до сих пор этого
West Africa, they still
Западная Африка они до сих пор на
speak French, yes, they, that is,
французском говорят да Они вот то есть
uh, then it turns out, uh, in fact, after the
ээ потом получается ээ по сути после
Second World War from  empires remained the
Второй мировой войны из империй остался
Soviet Union and to some extent
Советский Союз и в какой-то степени
China
Китай
Well China China yes They have China there -
Ну Китай Китай да Там же у них Китай -
it's an empire It has Tibet We
это империя У него же есть Тибет Мы
say we have 100 nationalities and in
говорим у нас 100 национальность а в
China in my opinion even more There is
Китае по-моему даже больше
Tibet yes a huge number
Там есть Тибет да огромное количество
there is Sinzyangursky island Chinese and the
есть Синзянгурский остро китайцы и
emperor Chinese Here That is it turns out
император китайцы Вот То есть получается
that history developed so that these
что история развивалась так что вот эти
empires already in the 20th century they were divided into
империи уже в XX веке они дробились на
national states Yes The Soviet
национальные государства Да Советский
Union was an attempt to restore the
Союз - это была попытка реставрации
Russian Empire in some other form
Российской империи в некой другой форме
Finland no longer existed Poland was no longer They
Уже не было Финляндии уже не было Польши
were able to cut off Ukraine
Смогли оттяпать назад Украину
Transcaucasia And Turkistan Central Asia
Закавказье Вот И Туркистан Среднюю Азию
and so on In the ninety-first year there
и так дальше В девяносто первом году
was a logical process of disintegration of this
логичный прошёл процесс распада вот этой
Russian Empire yes I call it the
Российской империи да Я его называю
second stage of the disintegration of the Russian Empire And
второй этап распада Российской империи И
now look the idea is that it has not
сейчас смотрите идея в том что это не
ended The Russian Federation in the
закончилось Российская Федерация в той
form in which it is now it is still an
форме в которой она сейчас есть она так
empire And in it there are these
и есть империя И в ней есть вот эти
national republics of compact
национальные республики компактного
residence Tatars Chechens
проживания татары чеченцы
Chuvashes this is Sakha And this process
чуваши это саха И этот процесс
continues If you remember if you
продолжается Вот если вы помните если вы
were in
были на
Transcaucasia and other places in the
Закавказье и в других местах в
nineties yes in the same Chechnya the
девяностых да в той же самой Чечне
percentage of Russians was quite
процент русских был довольно
high Now Now in Chechnya how many
высок Сейчас Сейчас в Чечне сколько
Russians I do
русских
n't know Well very few probably Zero yes In
Не знаю Ну очень мало наверно Ноль да В
Ingushetia zero
Ингушетии ноль
In Sakha Yakutia if we
В Саха Якутии если мы
look before the arrival of Soviet
смотрим до прихода советской
power local agricultural associations made up the
власти местные СХА составляли
majority During Soviet power there was a
большинство Во время советской власти
process of mixing of peoples They
было это процесс перемешивания народов
took Ukrainians Belarusians Russians
Брали там украинцев белорусов россиян
there to Kazakhstan to Sakha these here Uh they
туда в Казахстан в Саху этих сюда Ээ
did it so that Sakha became in
сделали так что Саха стала вот в
ninety-one when the Union once this is what
девяносто первом когда Союз раз это что
Yakutia And Yakutia yes the Republic of Sakha
Якутия А Якутия да Республика Сахана
is called Yes I Yes there were there were there were
называется Да я Да их стало их стало
less than 50% What 30% of Sakha was already yes
меньше 50% Что 30% саха уже было да
Because Russians settled Now in
Потому что позаселяли русские Сейчас за
30 years of independence yes of the Russian
30 п лет независимости да Российской
Federation in the agricultural association the last
Федерации в СХА последняя вот эта
census that you had agricultural associations have
перепись которая у вас была СХА стала
already become more than 50% That is to say non-native
уже больше 50% То есть не некоренное
population is leaving those regions
население уезжает с тех регионов потому
because during the Soviet Union
что во время Советского Союза привезли
they were brought to work the Union collapsed they  they left
их на работу Союз распался они поуезжали
for their own, as it were, uh, well, yes,
на свои как бы ээ ну да сократилось
production has decreased, this land or somewhere to the south
производство это земли или либо на юга
And then now a lot has been done,
куда-то И потом сейчас много же сделали
like this on a rotational basis, yes Therefore,
как это вахтовым способом да Поэтому
now, yes, now in Yakutia and Sakha, uh,
сейчас да сейчас в Якутии и Сахе ээ
indigenous people are more than 50% and this process is
коренных больше 50% и этот процесс
increasing That is, we see that in
увеличивается То есть мы смотрим что в
Russia, uh, the percentage of Russians in the national
России ээ процент русских в национальных
republics has fallen catastrophically, yes in
республиках катастрофически упал да в
Tatarstan, Bashkar-Tatarstan, and so on, yes
Татарстане Башкартастане и так дальше да
in all That is, they are already becoming
во все То есть они уже стают
mono-national states in essence, yes
мононациональными государствами по сути
Moreover, the percentage of Russians in the
да Больше того процент русских в
original Russian cities is steadily falling
исконно-русских городах неуклонно падает
You see that Tajiks are moving in,
Вы же видите что у вас заезжают таджики
there are Dagestanis, Chiyab, yes And well, as a problem
там дагестанцы чияб да И ну как проблема
for you, maybe a problem for us Ukrainians,
для вас может проблема для нас украинцев
this is just a good trend because,
это как раз хорошая тенденция потому что
uh, we see that this very
ээ мы видим что как раз вот этот
component will collapse, yes, will be the impetus for the
компонент и развалит да будет толчком к
collapse, this is the third stage of the collapse of the
развалу вот это третьему этапу развала
Russian Empire Because look
Российской империи Потому что посмотрите
in Petrograd in 1917, who actively
в Петрограде в 1917 году кто активное
participated in the revolution, uh,
участие в революции применял э
showed It was not
проявлял Не
Russians, really If we are not  Russians
русские правда Если мы по Это не русские
yes they were not Russians Well look all
да это не русские были Ну смотрите все
these Lenins Stalins all these communists
эти Ленины Сталины все эти коммунисты
they were either Jews or Georgians
они же были либо евреями либо грузинами
or Ukrainians yes there are these regiments of
либо украинцами да там вот эти полки
Ukrainians I watched
украин Я смотрел
it as this is the first composition
это как это первый состав
there were no Russians yes Oh what was it
там русских не было да Ой как он
called Rad People's Commissar or whatever he was And the
назывался Рад нарком или как он там А
government yes Yes yes there were more, there were more
правительство да Вот да там ну больше
Jews there were fewer Russians well
много было евреев там русских было
fewer non-Russians yes That is, it
меньше ну меньше не русских да То есть
turns out that the same thing is happening now
получается и сейчас сейчас происходит то
Look if we look at the
же самое Смотрите если мы смотрим ээ
national composition of let's say the top
национальный состав ээ скажем м высших
officials of the Russian Federation then we see
чинов Российской Федерации то мы видим
there Shaigu was a Tuvinian and what-what Shaigu is a
там Шайгу был Тувинец а что-что Шайгу
Tuvinian yes Then Yevkurov in your
Тувинец да Потом Евкуров у вас вот в
army yes Who is he This one from Ingu yes
армии да Он кто Этот из ингу да
Ingushetia yes Sobyanin he is also not Russian
Ингушетия да Собянин он тоже не русский
Who is Putin And he is no he is from Khanty there
Кто Путин А он нет он с Ханте туда
somewhere from Tyumen region He is someone there Khanty
где-то с Тюменщины Он кто-то там Хант
or Mansion he even looks I didn't understand
или Мансион он даже выглядит Не понял
Sobyanin Sobyanin Sobyanin A Sobyanin yes And
Собянин Собянин Собянин А Собянин да И
that is if we look like this yes that a
то есть если мы смотрим так да что
huge number and the number of Russians is
огромное количество и количество русских
decreasing earlier  in the power bloc if
уменьшается раньше в силовом блоке если
we look at the end of the nineties in the power
мы смотрим конец девяностых в силовом
bloc there the police as if in essence were
блоке там полиция как бы по сути было
Russian yes for example Ukrainians were not
русский да например украинцев не
allowed in the power bloc well in when the
допускали в силовом ну в когда был
Soviet Union collapsed
распад Советского Союза
Well ninety-
Ну девяносто
first of
первой
this KGB Remember No I can't say No
этой КГБ Помните Нет не могу сказать Нет
Perish
Периш
I don't remember whether he is a Letovets or a Latvian
Я не помню то ли он летовец то ли латыш
Latvian in my opinion or one of these yes
Латыш по-моему или или кто-то из этих да
Here But the main thing now if you
Вот Но основной сейчас если вы
look now in law enforcement
посмотрите сейчас в правоохранительных
agencies somehow there are a lot of Armenians
органах как-то стало очень много армян
Tajiks Azerbaijanis Chechens
таджиков азербайджанцев чеченцев
Dagestanis yes That is, there is an interception of
дагестанцев да То есть идёт перехват
control essentially in the power agencies If
управления по сути в силовые органы Если
we look at the graduates of the FSB Academy yes
мы посмотрим выпускники академии ФСБ да
graduates of the Ministry of Internal Affairs Academy a huge
выпускники академии МВД огромнейшее
number of non-Russians That is, earlier a
количество нерусских То есть раньше
non-Russian was perceived as a person
нерусский воспринимался как человек
who came from the republic and there
который приехал из республики да и там
somewhere either to work or something Now he is
где-то либо на работу или что Сейчас он
perceived as uh not just even a
воспринимается как ээ не просто даже
native resident of these cities but a
коренной уже житель этих городов а
person who has power Russians are
человек обладающий властью Русские
slowly moving away If you
потихоньку отодвигаются Если вы
look who owns the main
посмотрите кто владеет основными
businesses markets and so on it
бизнесами рынками и так дальше это же
will not be Russians
будет не русские
true  Here in Moscow is the Sadovod market I
правда Вот в Москве рынок садовод Я
think I don't need to tell you what
думаю мне не нужно вам рассказывать что
it is And to be honest, I didn't know about it I've
это И я про него честно говоря и не знал
never been there
Я там никогда не был
I just read about it that it
Я сейчас только прочитал про него что
turns out there are some Azerbaijani
оказывается там какие-то азербайджанские
billionaires there Yes Yes And what about some
миллиардеры Да Да Ещё что там какое-то
other enterprise Well, a huge, huge
ещё предприятие Ну огромное огромное
amount How much more than that during the
такое количество Сколько больше того при
Soviet Union was there a mosque in Moscow
Советском Союзе была мечеть в Москве
What-what was a mosque in Moscow during the
Что-что мечеть в Москве была при
Soviet Union There were a few but there were
Советском Союзе Быва немного но были
mosques Well, I don't remember exactly in Moscow Well, there were
мечети Ну в Москве не помню точно Ну
definitely mosques in Moscow They have also been
мечети точно были в Москве Они ещё
preserved, you know, since the
сохранили знаете
times, as they say, of the
э-э со времён как говорится ещё
healthy revolutionary era Well, maybe it is like that,
здореволюционных Ну может она как да
maybe it was like that In Moscow, by the way, there were a
может оно как было В Москве кстати очень
lot of these Tatars Tatars All the
много было та этих татар Татар Все
janitors in Moscow were Tatars by
дворники в Москве были татары между
the way So look now, now, uh,
прочим Так вот смотри сейчас сейчас вот
I think that the whole world saw how Quran
ээ я думаю что весь мир видел как Куран
Bayram was celebrated in Moscow and a
Байрам праздновался в Москве да и
huge number of these Muslims
огромное количество вот этих мусульман
on the street, yes, like that A hung, hung, hung Hung
на улице да вот так
up, yes Oh, and now, yes,
завис Развисли да О а вот сейчас да
hung, yes I'm telling you, you saw these yes
зависла да говорю и вы же видели эти да
photographs of how many Muslims celebrated Quran Bayrla in Moscow and St. Petersburg
фотографии сколько в Москве и в Питере
Beiram So excuse me, there lives uh I
Бейрам Так извини тут проживает ээ я
say there is a Pyaterochka under my window there are
говорю вон у меня под окно Пятёрочка там
all these either Uzbeks yes but they
все эти вот то ли узбеки да но они
know how here is one store only
знаете как вот одна один магазин одни
Uzbeks another store only Kyrgyz
узбеки другой магазин одни киргизы
the third Yes Yes They the thing is that
третий Да Да Они вот дело в том что
look they are very organized
смотрите они очень сильно организованы
Russians Here you go out you uh even with your
русские Вот вы выйдите вы ээ даже с
neighbor on the landing and even with your
соседом по площадке да и со своими
friends you are not organized If you are
друзьями вы не организованы Если вас
beaten on the street yes the rest
будут бить на улице да вот остальные
will somehow carefully go around or
будут там как-то осторожно обходить либо
somewhere there at most they will call the police
где-то там максимум позвонят в полицию
If yes if you beat there an Uzbek
Если да если вы будете бить там узбека
Tajik or there a Chechen yes a huge
таджика или там чеченца да огромное
number of them will gather and run out and beat
количество его собрать и выбежит и от
you with a thud the whole crowd Even
колашмать отт вас всей толпой Даже
more than that Not only if you
больше того Не то что если вы будете
beat but if that Tajik Uzbeks or there a
бить а если тот таджик узбеки или там
Dagestani beats you his brothers will
дагестанец будет бить вас его собратья
run out and beat you That is why the Russians are
выбегут и будут бить вас Поэтому русские
standing in their own country they are standing outcasts Here is a
стоют в своей стране они стоют изгоями
striking example yes this is Ramzan
Вот яркий приклад пример да это Рамзан
Kadyrov Here I think that you are a person who
Кадыров Вот я думаю что вы человек
was a military man with you  there is a concept of
который военный были у вас есть понятие
officer's honor were you an officer yes
там офицерская честь Вы офицер были да
What-what were you an officer yes or no Yes Yes Yes
Что-что вы офицер были да или нет Да Да
Here And when you look now
Да Вот И когда вы смотрите сейчас
probably at what Kadyrov and
наверное на то что вытворяет Кадыров и
his son are doing when they took this
его сын когда они брали там вот этого
Russian guy from Volgograd, brought him to the
русского парня из Волгограда привезли в
Grozny pretrial detention center and beat him up Did you see it or not Well, that
СИЗО Грозного и избивали Видели или нет
is, why can Kadyrov take a
Ну ну то есть почему Кадыров может взять
Russian from Volgograd, bring
русского из Волгограда привезти в
him to Grozny, bring his
Грозный себе в СИЗО привести туда своего
fifteen-year-old son there to the pretrial detention center, beat
пятнадцатилетнего сына избивать на
this defenseless Russian guy on camera,
камеру этого беззащитного парня русского
film it and post it on
снимать это на видео и выкладывать в
Instagram
Instagram ещё
I'm telling you that this is a very big problem for us
Я же вам говорю что это для нас очень
And what you're saying now is all taking
И то что вот вы сейчас говорите это всё
place I don't object I'm not
имеет место быть Я же не возражаю Я не
saying that this doesn't exist It
тоже говорю что этого нету Это есть
turns out the question The question now do you
Получается вопрос Вопрос сейчас
understand what the matter is Here about, uh, the
понимаете в чём дело Тут насчёт
preservation of the state You are
ээ вот сохранения государства Вы
absolutely right that this is the
абсолютно правы что вот это вот
collapse of Russia yes, for a separate
развал России да вот на отдельное
principality, uh, the
княжество
thing is that if there are people, well,
ээ дело в том что если есть люди ну люди
more or less reasonable people and thinking people
более-менее разумные да и думающие
should understand that every collapse
должны понимать что всякий развал он
ends in a big massacre Well,
заканчивается большой резнёй
yes it will be  rusare this is definitely Well, you
Ну да будет русаре это однозначно Ну вы
see here, you understand, here it turns
же видите тут тут понимаете тут ээ
out that such a choice Either it means
получается такая вот выбор Либо значит
if it goes down this path of collapse, then
если пойдёт по этому пути развала значит
expect a great
жди большой
massacre
резни
And how can no pen or liver
И как это никакие перо эти печенки не
help By the way, the thing is that look, not a
помогут Кстати дело в том что смотри не
great massacre, a great massacre is already
большая резня большая резня уже
inevitable Either there will be collapse or there will be no
неминуема Либо будет развал либо не
collapse The thing is that you dont
будет развала Дело дело в том что не
have to be a prophet Well, I wont say you
надо быть пророком Вот не я я скажу вы
saw whats happening in Syria yes because there is a
видели что в Сирии да потому что
tendency yes but to say that its
тенденция есть да но говорить о том что
inevitable I Look, you saw whats
это неизбежно я Смотри вы видели что в
happening in Syria these days yes How the
Сирии происходит эти дни да Как вот
victorious HTS group is cracking down,
победившая группировка ХТШ расправляется
doing ethnic cleansing of the Olovites, Druze,
делает этнические чистки оловитов друзов
Yezidis You saw these yes, in any case, shots Thats how it is The
эзидов Видели эти да по-любому кадры Вот
thing is that now
так Дело в том что сейчас
this non-Russian component is not yet
вот эта нерусская компонент он ещё не
so
настолько
much of it in Russia yes that it would
много его в России да чтобы он уже
dictate its power But already in schools, if
диктовал свою силу Но уже в школах если
we look, yes, in many schools there is
мы посмотрим да во многих школах есть
such a thing that Russians already constitute a
такое что русские уже составляют
minority That is, we are looking at a
меньшинство То есть мы же смотрим
generation yes For example, if we take your
поколение да Например если возьмём ваш
age, then Russians are still the majority If
возраст то русских ещё большинство Если
we take  children youth already a completely
мы возьмём дети молодёжь уже совсем
different balance is obtained And regardless of whether it
другой баланс получается И независимо от
disintegrates or does not disintegrate
того или распадётся да или не распадётся
this component will increase and the
этот компонент будет увеличиваться и
confrontation between non-Russians and
противостояние между нерусскими и
Russians will increase Moreover,
русскими будет возрастать Тем более
look, uh, if we take the times of the
посмотрите ээ если мы возьмём времена
Russian Empire, yes, all these nobles,
Российской империи да все эти дворяне
they all went through cadet schools,
все они там проходили кадетские училища
military, everything Now we look, yes, all
военные всё Сейчас мы смотрим да все
non-Russians are engaged in martial arts,
нерусские занимаются боевыми искусствами
there MMA and so on, yes I apologize for the fact that
там MMA и так дальше да Я прошу прощения
these military
вот насчёт того что вот эти военные
schools and so on, oh, nobles, yes But
училища и так далее ой дворяне да А ведь
look how many
смотрите сколько ээ
non-Russians were at court, let's
нерусских были при дворе будем так
say so Well, these were yes, these were either
говорить Ну а это были да это были либо
Germans, cowards, Poles, yes, not only
немцы трусы поляки да не только
Yusupov Who is Yusupov a Tatar Yes, there were very many Tatars
Юсупов Кто Юсупов татарин Да Татарские
You know, there were a
были очень Вот вы знаете очень
lot of nobles, their descendants had
много дворян были их потомки были
Tatar crusts, because when
татарские корки были потому что когда
this Golden Rda was even
вот это вот Золотая Рда даже там
conquered there, the Kazan Khanate, well, all
завоёвывали Казанское ханство там ну все
these remnants of the Golden Horde, then these
эти остатки Золотой Орды то вот этих вот
guys who were murzas or
ребят которые ну были мурзами там или
other things, yes, absolutely right, the tsars made
прочее да абсолютно верно цари делали
these  their close associates there and gave
этими своими приближёнными там и давали
them a Slavicized surname there
им славянизированную фамилию там
Karamurzin it was Karamurza yes or
Карамурзин это был Карамурза да или
Karamzin yes take yes that's well if we
Карамзин да взять да вот это ну если мы
look yes no look the nobility of the
посмотрим да нет смотрите дворянство
nobility there was
дворян
almost no
рукого почти не было Почти не было
Russian nobility They were Lermontovs
дворянства русского Они были лермонтов
These were from the Lermont family the Scots were Yes and
Это из рода Лермонт шотландцы были Да И
so
так
on How many Poles were there very but
дальше Сколько поляков было очень но
look no need no need to confuse the Tatars of
смотрите не надо не надо путать татар
that year yes the 19th century and the Islamists of
того года да XIX века и исламистов
today
современных
If we look even let's say Dagestan of the 10th
Если мы посмотрим даже скажем Дагестан X
century it still was not a bearer of
века он всё-таки не был носителем
radical Islam as it is now
радикального ислама как есть сейчас
You know radical Islam the same
Вы знаете радикальный ислам тот же
Wahhabism it has very deep roots
вахабизм он имеет очень глубокие корни
It existed before yes but it was not so
Он и и раньше был да но не так был
widespread Sorry I had an
распространён Извините я у меня была
interesting book like that unfortunately I
книжка интересная такая к сожалению я её
hid it somewhere well lost in short That's what was
где-то по ну заныкал потерял короче Вот
called oh religions of the East Yeah
называлось ой религии востока Угу
And there just like that well as they say in
И там как раз вот ну как говорится
such an accessible language it
доходчивым таким языком
was
было
described how this Judaism was born
расписано как зародился вот этот иудаизм
Yeah It was Zooastrism like some well as the
Угу Это зооастризм был как какой ну как
sources of this  Judaism there uh
бы источники вот этого иудаизма там ээ
monotheism And then, then,
единобожие И как потом значит появилось
Christianity appeared Then, then, this is Islam, well,
христианство Потом значит это ислам ну
this is the forerunner, as they say, uh, three branches,
это предвета как говорится ээ триветви
let's say, of one
будем так говорить одного
uh, well, one religion, or what can I
ээ ну одной религии что ли или как это
say? It just kind of went and
сказать Это же просто как бы пошёл а
then these branches began to divide again
потом эти ветви ещё ещё начали делиться
Yes, yes, here And regarding this radical,
Да да Вот И насчёт этого радикального
by the way, this is characteristic not only of, say,
это кстати характерно не только допустим
Islam Christians too Well, Christianity
исламу Христиане тоже Ну христианство
Christ's campaigns were also
Христовые походы были тоже
Catholics, Orthodox, there, Protestants
католики православные там протестанты
cut each other in general God forbid
резали себя друг друга вообще Дай боже
Yes, if we take it from history, they sinned there
да Да если так взять по истории они там
But yes, but look, the thing is that, let's say,
Но да но смотрите дело в том что скажем
this was a feature of an archaic society,
это была особенность архаичного общества
yes, cruelty, this uh, genocide of everyone
да жестокость вот эта ээ геноцид всех
who differs from you there ethnically, uh,
которые отличаются от тебя там этнически
in some other way, Europe has already
э по другим каким-том Европа уже-то
outgrown Europe does not live in an archaic
переросла Европа живёт не в архаичном
society, but in an industrial and even
обществе а в индустриальном и даже
post-industrial Soviet society,
постиндустриальном Советское общество
no matter how it was, yes, it was an
как бы так не было да оно было
industrial, urban society It
индустриальное общество городское Э оно
somehow tried to clean out this archaism After the fall of the
как-то старалось вычищать После падения
USSR, in
СССР в
Russia, let's say, there was a very tough
России в скажем прошла очень жёсткая
Islamization of these regions Look
исламизация этих регионов Посмотрите
Jahar Dudayev yes, in fact, he was a secular
Джахар Дудаев да по сути он был светский
Russian Soviet general There
российский советский генерал
were many of them Well, a modern one, that is, uh, a
Их много было Ну современный то есть ээ
modern Chechen figure, yes, in
современный чеченский деятель да уже по
fact, a Wahhabi Take Kadyrov, he
сути вахабит Вы возьмите Кадырова он
seems to say one thing, you need
вроде как говорит одно оно вам надо
a little Excuse me, I say, I just
немножко Извините я я говорите я просто
open it, otherwise, Yeah,
открываю а то Угу
Just the door is open and
Просто дверь открытая и
creaks, Squeak, well, it just gets on your nerves It
скрипит Поскри ну просто на нервы
opens it, then closes it You
действует То откроет то закроется Вот
see, Wahhabism is one of the
понимаете Вахабизм - это же одно из
confluences of Islam, you just understand Therefore,
стечений ислама просто понимаете Поэтому
all, uh, well, it is radical there and so
все ээ ну оно радикальное там и так
on and so forth Of course, there are
далее и тому подобное Конечно там есть
certain
определённые
subtleties there
тонкости
But you can't call everyone Wahhabis
Вот Но всех называть вахобитами это
right away Yeah, you can't They,
сразу Угу
too, look how many of
нельзя Их же тоже вот смотрите сколько
these are in Islam, there are Alawites, Sunnis, Shiites,
этих в исламе там алавиты сунниты шииты
Shiites, yes And they don't divide it any further Yes,
Шиты да И ещё там дальше не делятся Да
I think there are about ten of them there, in that,
Там их по-моему порядка десяти там в том
look, it's the same as with
что смотрите это ж так же как с
Christianity, yes It was further
христианством было да Оно дальше
divided depending on regional
дробилось в зависимости от региональных
characteristics, on national
особенностей от национальных
characteristics Yes Yes Here And they
особенностей Да Да Вот И они же у них
even have languages, in general, many are different
даже языки-то в общем-то у многих разные
If here  let's take for example these Maghreb
Если вот взять допустим ээ этих Магриб
yes Maghreb well this is North Africa well this is
да Магриб ну это Северная Африка ну это
where the Arab conquest Western
где арабское завоевание Западная
North Africa They have completely
Северная Африка Они же у них совершенно
different
сильно отличаются
languages more than, say, Russian from
язык больше чем допустим русский от
Ukrainian yes The thing is that look at the
украинского да Дело в том что смотрите
territory of the Maghreb yes in fact these were
территория Магриба да по сути это жили
different peoples who lived there who were conquered by the
разные народы которые были завоёваны
Arabs and Arabized There are Berbers
арабами и арабизировались Там и берберы
and others like that maka Moroccans
и другие как бы так вот мака мароканцы
yes if you take the inhabitants of
да если взять и жители Египта
modern Egypt yes it seems like both are like
современного да вроде и те и те как бы
Arabs yes the Arab world yes but
арабы да арабский мир да но немножко
they call themselves a little different they just call themselves But here is a
разные они себя называют просто Но тут
small nuance Everyone reads the Koran in
маленький нюанс Все читают Коран на
Arabic In Arabic only in Arabic
арабском На арабском только на арабском
And they do not recognize any translation This is
И не признают ни один перевод Вот
absolutely the same situation
абсолютно абсолютно такая ситуация была
with Christianity yes It was read in Latin
с христианством да Его читали на латыне
Everything was in Latin Yes Well Catholics No
Всё на латыне было Да Ну католиков Нет
at first everything was in Latin Then yes
сначала всё на латыни было Потом да
then uh because of the fact that Greece uh essentially
потом ээ из-за того что гре ээ по сути
Byzantium yes like the Eastern Roman
Византии да как бы Восточная Римская
Empire became such a different center of power
империя стала таким другим центром силы
yes there uh it became in Greek essentially there were
да там ээ стал на греческом по сути было
two poles yes when Vladimir baptized
два полюса да когда Владимир крестил
Rus' yes in fact  uh these monks who
Русь да по сути ээ эти монахи которые
came here they who were They were
сюда приезжали они кто были Они были
Greeks essentially Greek missars like
греками по сути Греческие миссары типа
yes from Byzantium Here and into national
да из из Византии Вот И на национальные
languages the Bible began to be translated later
языки Библию начали переводить уже в
later when more
позже позже когда началось больше
national self-awareness began and began until a
национальное самосознание и началось до
certain point it was not recognized
определённого момента это не признавали
If we take
Если мы возьмём
in Russia yes still if I'm not
в России да до сих пор если я не
mistaken yes Russian Orthodox
ошибаюсь да Русская православная
Russian Orthodox Church uh
Российская православная церковь ээ
reads the service in Church Slavonic
читает службу на церковно-славянском
Yes Yes This is an artificial language
языке Да Да Это искусственный язык
that was specially created for
который специально был создан для
worship Uh like that it was like an
богослужения Э-э вот такого он был как
international language Maybe
бы интернациональным языком Может быть
it uh not really uh created It seems to me that it is
он ээ не очень ээ создан Мне кажется это
more natural No Church
более естественный Нет церковно
Church Slavonic it is based on
церковно-славянский он на основе
Old Bulgarian It is an artificial language
староболгарского Это искусственный язык
simply Yes yes I say well again it
просто Да да я говорю ну он опять же
had some kind of basis You are not just
какую-то основу-то имел Ты же не просто
its Old Bulgarian yes it is the same thing
его староболгарский да это то же самое
receive A you see and Latin turned out the other
получа А видите а латынь получилась
way around
наоборот
Laten it is well considered like a dead
Латень это ну считается как бы мёртвым
language and it is only used well
языком и она только используется ну вот
in science that's what is fashionable as in its
в науке вот вот это модно как в своё
time so that  they taught in
время чтоб учили-то на
Latin in Europe, that's
латыне в Европе-то
why we say that we have all these
Поэтому и мы говорим что у нас все эти
words, uh, most of these
слова ээ большинство вот этих
technical ones,
технических
they have the same roots because that's where
они жеские корни потому что вот оттуда
everything came from and these terms, sho Well, look, I'd also like to, it's
всё шло и термины эти шо Вот э смотрите
interesting, we
ещё хотелось бы вот интересно вот с вами
can talk to you adequately, how do you
вроде адекватно можно поговорить Как вы
rate it, you lived in the Soviet Union,
оцениваете вот вы жили в Советском Союзе
I was in 1981, you were
я восемьдесят первого года вы там
older there, you saw the science, the
постарше вы видели науко
scientific and technical potential of the Soviet
научно-технический потенциал Советского
Union, and so on. And now, when they
Союза и так дальше И сейчас когда вот
say that Russia can't make its own
говорят что Россия не может сделать свой
passenger plane and they already want to
пассажирский самолёт и уже хотят
go back to the cornfields and the And2 or whatever,
вернуться к кукурузникам да Анд2 или что
how did it happen that in 30
там вот как так получилось что ээ за 30
years there was such a degradation of the
лет прошла такая деградация
scientific and technical
научно-технического
potential, Uh, how can I formulate this better?
потенциала Э так как бы это вот лучше
After the civil war there was such a
после гражданской войны был такой
surge in development, yes, you must agree, there were
всплеск развития да согласитесь были
factories, this is the elimination of
заводы это самое ликвидация
illiteracy, and so on.
неграмотности и так далее
And the Soviet Union developed at
И Советский Союз развивался очень
such a high rate. Yeah, with the
такими высокими темпами Угу при
help of I don't want to deny that they
помощи Я не хочу отрицать то что там
brought engineers from Europe, they came from America, and so
привозили инженеров из Европы из Америки
on. But
приезжали там прочее Вот Но
this is, how can I tell you, the centralization of
вот это как бы вам сказать централизация
power and ideology.
власти и идеология
Often
Вот зачастую
we don't
мы не
we take how to say we underestimate the role of
берём как сказать недооцениваем роль
ideology in people's lives yes But if we
идеологии в жизни людей да Но если мы
look we compare in Europe somehow there is
посмотрим мы сравним в Европе как-то
no centralization of such power
нету централизации такой власти
ideology In America there was no
идеологии В Америке не было
centralization of power and ideology yes How
централизации власти и идеологии да Как
can they develop give
они могут развиваться давать
high-tech things E take uh
высокотехнологические вещи Е взять ээ
Germany yes with comrade Portin Genos
Германию да с товарищем портайном генос
to some yes No so that would have been what it was long ago
некоторым да Нет так тот давно бы какая
and this is the same ideology Well I'm saying
была и это самое идеология Ну я говорю
now in the same America excuse me in the same America the ideology of the
вот сейчас ве той же Америки извините в
dollar They also have their own ideology This is
доллара У них тоже своя идеология Это
also an ideology
тоже идеология
Well how to look let's do it this way Ninety-
Ну как бы смотрите давайте так Девяносто
first year Here you asked me but I can't finish yes
первый год Вот вы меня спросили а
Let's finish I apologize Yeah
договорить мне не да Давайте договорите
Then you can ask this how to
Я прошу прощения Угу Потом вы можете это
say so questions but
самое как так сказать задать вопросы но
I say in fact there was a single ideology there
я говорю по факту была единая идеология
was
была
quite
централизация достаточно
rigid centralization which in general allowed by the
жёсткая что в общем-то и позволило
way to stand up
кстати и выстоять ээ
against uh fascists
против ээ фашистов
Nazis Here
нацистов Вот
And then the crisis of
А потом значит начался кризис
ideology began Here at one
идеологии Вот в своё
time they somehow described that socialism is the
время как-то расписали что вот социализм
first stage of communism we all
первая стадия коммунизма мы же всё
built communism
коммунизм же строили
And
И
he uh  these are the main, well, how can I say, the
он ээ вот эти основные м ну как сказать
building blocks of this socialism were
ээ кирпичики вот этого социализма были
built by Lenin. Lenin in his
выстроены ещё Лениным Ещё Ленин в своих
works back in the twenties before his
трудах ещё в двадцатых годах до до своей
death, he already wrote about it there, how to
смерти он уже писал об этом там как
organize a rapkrin for us, a state of
устроить там нам рапкрин там государство
revolution, and so on and so forth. Yes, that's a
революции и прочее прочее да Вот там это
whole science. Although he scolds
же целая наука Он хотя вот его ругает но
him, his head worked well, he wrote a lot.
у него голова хорошо работала он много
And that period, that period,
написал И вот этот вот период период ещё
that was such a sharp, fairly
ээ вот это было такое резкое достаточно
intensive development. And the Soviet Union, after all,
ну интенсивное развитие И Советский Союз
in many respects was ahead of the
ведь по многим параметрам обгонял и
most developed countries, the same America.
самые развитые страны ту же Америку
No, that's understandable. Yes. And why did they
Нет так это понятно да А почему вот
stop now? Not me, just a minute. But
перестали сейчас Не я сейчас минуточку А
then the crisis of ideology began when
вот потом начался кризис идеологии когда
we ourselves began to tell jokes about
мы сами стали рассказывать анекдоты про
communism. Like communism will be, you know,
коммунизму Типа коммунизм будет знаете
when people's hands will not be so
когда когда у людей руки будут не так
visible and will not grow like that, but like that.
вот видно да не так расти а вот так
You know
Знаете
why. So as not to rake in for themselves, but to rake
почему Чтобы не под себя грести а от
away from themselves. Yeah, those are the jokes. And that's
себя отгребать Угу Такие анекдоты И оно
how it turned out. And then, let's
так и получилось А потом ээ если
say, the same revolution was made by, well,
допустим ту же самую революцию делали ну
how can I say, people who believed in
ээ как сказать люди которые верили в
this ideology katovskie for example there on
эту идеологию катовские например там на
Yes they are not just supporters they are like this
Да они не просто сторонники они как это
other word something flew out of my
ещё слово что-то вылетело из
head heptas or whatever it is Here
головы гепты или как там ещё Вот
And they sincerely believed that they could
И они искренне верили что может
build
построить
communism And then the party began to quickly quickly quickly quickly well
коммунизм А потом партия начала быстро
as they say to
быстро ну как говорится
increase Do you know how many
увеличиваться Знаете сколько было
Bolsheviks there were in the seventeenth year Look
большевиков в семнадцатом году Смотрите
I understood this I understood I can't And when And
я понял это Я понял Я не могу А когда А
in ninety-first there were almost 20 million
в девяносто первом было почти 20 млн
Let's do it this way I can't understand why for
Давайте так Я не могу понять почему
example I you asked me I say here
например я вы меня спросили я говорю вот
you are not getting me again Let's short here
вы меня опять не дос Давайте короче вот
you are very many the party ceased to be a
вы очень много партия перестала быть
communist
коммунистической
party already to everyone
партией уже ко всем
else But ninety-first year the collapse of the
остальным Но девяносто первый год развал
Soviet Union Why now yes for
Советского Союза Почему сейчас да
example Latvia Lithuania Estonia lives
например Латвия Литва Эстония живёт
better than the Pskov region What is the
лучше чем Псковская область Какая Рядом
Pskov region next to Estonia Why the
вот с Эстонией Псковская область Почему
standard of living in Latvia salaries are all higher
уровень жизни в Латвии зарплаты всё выше
than in the neighboring Pskov region You
чем в соседней Псковской области Вы
know I'll tell you this Less
знаете я вам скажу такую вещь Меньше
steals
ворует
That's my opinion I say less steals Yeah
Вот моё мнение я говорю меньше ворует
Well you read there on the computer
Ну вот вы же читаете там в в компьютере
these scandals Who is there at  they
вот эти скандалы Кого там у нас этих
started to put us in jail, these generals who are worth
генералов там начали сажать которые там
billions there, yes, yes, so what do you
там вообще миллиардные да Да Ну и что вы
want? What region did you say?
хотите А что там Какую вы сказали
Pskov Pskov yes, yes, so
область Псковская Псковская да Да Ну и
what? What do you think there? Okay, but just for the
что А вы что думаете там Хорошо А вот
sake of interest, I'll ask you this question.
вот ради интереса вот скажу такой вопрос
Maybe you're scared to talk about
вот может вам страшно рассуждать на
this topic, but it's interesting. If you have
такую тему но интересно Вот если у вас
top generals with such billions there,
топ-генералы с такими миллиардными там
these sums, yes, were taken, what do you
вот этими суммами да были взяты как вы
think? Putin and his inner circle are
считаете Путин и его ближнее окружение
involved in all these corruption
замешаны во всех этих коррупционных
cases, or do they not know about them? You know, in order to
делах или они не знают о них Вы знаете
say such things, you need to have
чтобы говорить такие вещи
information and exchange it with
надовладеть информацией а её уменять и
iron balls. I'll say that yes,
железными яйцами Я скажу что да потому
because I see it. It's obvious enough.
что я это вижу Это очевидно достаточно
I don't say what you think, you do
Не я говорю как вы думаете вы меня ваши
n't want to talk about your assumptions. It's already
предположения не хочу говорить Оно и так
so obvious that there's no point in even
настолько очевидно что нечего даже
asking such stupid questions. But it's
вопросы такие дурацкие задавать Но
scary to answer. Yes, provocative,
страшно отвечать да О провокацион
provocative. Does Putin steal and
провокационный да Ворует ли Путин и
immediately this is a provocative question. This is an
сразу это провокационный вопрос это
obvious answer, but this is a provocative
очевидный ответ но это провокационный
question. Do you know how this deputy minister, oh
вопрос Знаете как этого замминистр это
damn, his last name is Ivanov, I think,
уж ой блин фамилия Иванов по-моему
who  stole so much and did
который так много наворовал а Шайгу
n't know anything about Shaigu Oh, my God,
ничего не знал Его надо же Ой дяденьки
Shaigu And why did you need glasses? Didn't you have glasses? Didn't
Шайгу И что ж тебе очки надо было Очков
see or know? Yes Yes
нету что ли было Не видел не знал Да Да
Guys, you're asking a question that's
Ребят ну вы задаёте такой вопрос что в
pretty obvious Obvious The same thing
общем-то он достаточно очевиден Очевиде
Sorry, you don't
То же самое Извините и у вас такая же не
need the same thing Yes, we do too But what do you think? Do
надо Да у нас тоже А вот как вы считаете
you support the war against
ээ поддерживаете ли вы войну против
Ukraine? That's what Putin unleashed A
Украины Вот то что Путин развязал
provocative question War War is hard to
Провокационный вопрос Войну войну трудно
support but you understand I'll tell you
поддерживать но понимаете я вам скажу
this If Russia doesn't get
такую вещь Если э-э Россия не добьётся
its way it may fall apart And if it
своего она может посыпаться А если она
falls apart, that's what will happen What
посыпется вот получится вот то о чё то
I'm most afraid of It's the
чего я вот больше всего боюсь Это вот ээ
disintegration into these little principalities and
распад на эти вот маленькие княжества и
endless slaughter That's
бесконечная резня
why you see I'm saying I have
Вот поэтому вот вот понимаете я говорю я
nothing against it I don't think that the
не ничего против не имею не считаю что
Ukrainian people are vile and
там украинский подлый народ там и прочее
all that stuff That is, you support the war
всякого То есть вы поддерживаете войну
against Ukraine yes And you only know
против Украины да И только знаете из-за
why Out of a sense of self-preservation
чего Из само из чувства самосохранения
yes That is, because you understand that
да То есть потому что вы понимаете что
if Russia  will be defeated now yes
если Россия потерпит поражение сейчас да
then after this yes no It will definitely
то за этим да не может Она однозначно
crumble yes because of all these problems
посыпется да потому что все эти проблемы
Yes Yes And by the way I'll tell you this
Да Да И кстати я вам скажу такую вещь
You say there uh Russians not
Вот вы говорите там э-э русские не
Russian clans and so on That's where even the unity comes from, let's say uh
русские кланы и прочее Вот даже откуда
well as they say these what's their name
ээ ну как говорится этих как его
oligarchs
олигархов
and our rulers the same well
и правителей наших того же ну говорит
Putin says there it's not necessary he says only here
Путин там же не надо говорит только вот
I'm already Yeah Viz Viz Viz Vizla
меня уже
Oh it's hanging Yeah Everything is not hanging You
О развисло Угу Всё не развисло Вот
see And they, let's say,
понимаете И они же ведь допустим вот
grabbed it with this privatization and
нахапали да вот этой приватизации а
now this money that they have, they
теперь эти деньги которые у них есть их
need to
же надо
protect It's all the same, you know
защищать Это вот е всё равно что знаете
as they say
как говорится
here's who else it is Martven, I think, has something like this
вот ещё кто это У Мартвена по-моему есть
: "If you have 10 dollars in your pocket
такое говорит: "Если у тебя в кармане 10
then these 10 dollars belong to
долларов то эти 10 долларов принадлежат
you" And if you have a million then you
тебе" А если у тебя миллион то ты
belong to this
принадлежишь этому
million There is such an
миллиону Есть
expression Haven't heard
такое та такое выражение Не слышали
No And these people who are already with
Нет И вот эти люди которые уже у
them You read Kadol no
них Вы же Кадол читали нет
Love time doesn't wait
Люби время не ждёт
No there are interesting ones and this is not even a
Нет там интересны есть и вот это даже не
story  but rather a novella
рассказ а скорее новела
Eh, in short, about a
Ээ короче про
gold digger who means
золотоискателя который значит
[laughter]
[смех]
well, Klandai, that's the thing, he
ну кландай это самое на это на Аляске
dug up a little bit of
там накопал что-то там немножко
gold in Alaska, came to America, well, he was already
золотишко приехал в Америку ну уже
quite rich, and he
достаточно богатым и он там
started doing
начал занялся
business there, and he continued to get rich, get rich, get rich
бизнесом и он стал дальше богатеть
And he had a
богатеть богатеть А у него была
secretary who, well, not by
секретарша которая в общем-то ну так не
accident, he took her He fell in love with her, and he
нароком взял Он в её влюбился и и он
proposed to her, as they say, so that she would
предложил ей как говорится чтобы она
marry Maybe she says: "I wo
вышла изница Может она говорит: "Я за
n't marry you" When you came,
вас не пойду" Когда вот вы пришли
came from this Alaska, yes, from this
приехали с этого с Аляски да с этого
Klandai, yes, look at yourself, what are
кландайка да вы посмотрите на себя какие
you like, how were you then, toned up, he
вы как каким вы были тогда подтянутым
says there, and now he says, what do you
там говорит а сейчас говорит что вы себя
imagine yourself as flabby, you-you And you don't, he
представляете обрюший там ты-ты И вы не
says, you won't belong to me, you
вы говорит не будете принадлежать мне вы
will belong to your
будете принадлежать своим
millions And then he took everything, threw it all down,
миллионам И тогда он взял всё бросил
bought it earlier, married this one, and well, like in a
купил раньше на этой женился и ну как в
fairy tale, so that they would live happily and
сказке да чтобы и жили они счастливы и
die out in one free god Well, you
вымерли в один халярный бог Вот Ну это
need to read this Or here's Martin Eden I why
надо читать Или вот Мартин Иден Я почему
these American ones, they have
вот эти именно американские у них ведь
this too  uh guys thought about this
тоже там это ээ ребята думали об этом
Hemingway let's say this what's his name Henry I've
Хамингуэя допустим этот как его у Генри
already flown away a little somewhere what are
Я уже я уже немножко улетел где-то о чём
we talking about I don't quite understand a little
мы говорим Немножко не совсем понимаю
Yes yes I'm talking about this
Вот Дада Вот я говорю вот насчёт этой
war Therefore this is a
войны Поэтому вот это получается
certain unity, namely a sense of
определённая единение именно чувство
self-preservation
самосохранения
If it doesn't work out if you don't get it then
Если не получится если не получи то вы
you are supporting the destruction of
получается вы поддерживаете уничтожение
Ukraine in order for destruction to be a speech
Украины для того чтобы уничтожение речь
well the war is going on the war is going on in the war
ну война идёт война идёт в войне
another state is being destroyed yes That is to
уничтожается другое государство да То
say in this war you are
есть получается в этой войне вы
supporting the destruction of Ukraine so that as a
поддерживаете уничтожение Украины чтобы
result if Russia doesn't succeed the
в результате если у России не получится
goal of the SVO yes then the Russian Federation will fall apart
цели СВО да то распадётся Российская
and you will be in a bad way I understand Well yes Well
Федерация и у вас будет плохо Я понял
and about the fact that
Ну да Вот Ну а насчёт того что
destruction well here of course you're exaggerating a little
уничтожение ну тут конечно вы немножко
Well how Let's look
преувеличите Ну как Давайте посмотрите
The city of Bakhmut 70,000 people lived there How many people
Город Бахмут жило 70.000 населения
live there now There
Сколько сейчас там живёт
were battles there yes The city was destroyed Well the city of
Так там бои были да Город уничтожен Ну
seventy thousand The speech is
город семидесятитысячный город Речь-то
not about the occupation of all of Ukraine Once
не идёт о том об оккупации все Украины
again the point is not the occupation Well the city was
Ещё раз суть не в том оккупаци Ну город
destroyed The speech is The speech is After all you
уничто Реч идёт Речь идёт Ведь вы вот
also
тоже
don't listen after all the speech is not about the fact
не послушайте ведь речь не идёт о том
that  destroy Ukraine or
что вот уничтожит именно Украину или там
make all Ukrainians Russians This is what we are
всех украинцев сделать русскими Это об
talking about Yes This is what We
этом речь идёт Да Это вот о чём О чём
are talking about You have chosen for yourself that you are
идёт речь Вы выбрали себе вот что вы вот
Ukrainians that you are being treated like that And what are we talking about
украинцы что вас вые так А о чём идёт
then I cannot understand what you are
речь тогда Я не могу понять за что вы
fighting for But you understand what the matter is
воюете Но понимае понимаете в чём дело
Uh, with all the uh, well, how can I say, with respect
Ээ при всей ээ ну как сказать м уважении
and understanding of the sovereignty of the independence of the
и понимания суверенитета независимости
state, it is also necessary to understand that
государства необходимо ещё понимать что
uh, independence and
ээ независимость и
sovereignty do not mean that you can do it
суверенитет это не значит что хочешь то
This is exactly what you can
Это как раз и значит что хочешь то и
do No, that does not happen This is the
делай Нет такого не бывает Это то же
same as - there is I say that they
самое как - существует я говорю вот
often say there are international
часто же говорят там международные
rules, international
правила международные
treaties so as not to
договоры чтобы не
be, not to create a threat or inconvenience,
быть не создавать угрозу или неудобство
so to speak, a neighbor So what I understood
так сказать сосед Так то какой я понял
what I simply cannot understand If you do not
какая я просто не могу понять Если вы не
want to occupy Ukraine, to seize
хотите оккупировать Украину захватить
Kyiv, what is your goal and how do you see it I
Киев какая ваша цель и как вы её видите
cannot understand Why is it needed Okay Well,
Не могу понять Зачем он нужен Хорошо Ну
how will you win I will tell you this
как вы выиграете Вот вам скажу такую
thing Uh,
вещь Ээ вот
uh, to seize Kyiv and destroy
ээ захватывать там Киев да и уничтожать
Ukraine But you have so many
Украину На у вас столько
debts, look at the question, the question How are you
долгов смотри вопрос вопрос Как вы
going to
собираетесь
Explain well Here I am  for example, I
Хорошо объясните Вот я я например
pay So look, I see
выплачивать Так что смотрите я вижу как
how if Russia captured Kyiv and
что если бы Россия захватила Киев да
put some kind of its own
поставила б там какое-то своё
marine government there and it
маринеточное правительство и оно
signed everything it wants for capitulation
подписала там всё что хочет капитуляции
yes How are you going to get Ukraine to
да Как вы собираетесь чтобы Украина
sign the capitulation yes if you don't capture
подписала капитуляцию да если вы не
Kyiv
захватываете Киев
So it's not capitulation we're not talking about
Так не капитуляция речь идёт не о
capitulation
капитуляции
What about Well, let's do it this way What is the goal Do you
А что Ну давайте так Какая цель Вы
want to keep Donetsk, Lugansk, Crimea,
хотите оставить себе Донецк Луганск Крым
Zaporizhia region, there, Kherson yes That's it
Запорожскую область там Херсонскую да
I, to be honest, do
Вот это вот я я вообще честно говоря так
n't really understand It's not well, maybe
не очень понимаю Это вот не ну может
Kherson and Kherson and this
быть Херсонская и Херсон и вот это
Zaporizhia may just be something like a
Запорожье может быть просто то что как
buffer zone from Crimea That could be well, that's how it is
бы буферная зона от Крыма Вот это может
Let's do it this way
ну вот как смо Давай давайте так
Look, this is what can what can
Смотрите вот что может что может
force Zelensky to sign Here
заставить Зеленского подписать Вот
Zelensky, if you don't capture
Зеленский если вы не захватите
Zelensky and Kyiv and don't put
Зеленского и Киев да и не поставите туда
your Yanukovych there, no one will sign Well, it's
своё Януковича никто не подпишет
not he who will sign, someone else will sign What Well, who will
Ну не он подпишет другой подпишет Что
appoint someone there It's not the point that,
Ну кого назначит кого-нибудь там Не дело
look, the person who will
в том что смотрите человек который
come out and say in Kyiv:  "I will
выйдет и в Киеве скажет: "Я буду
sign there, uh, the transfer of territories, he will
подписывать там ээ отдачу территорий его
not be there in an hour" You see, you
ж через час не будет уже" Понимаете Вы
know how many of
знаете сколько сколько существует всяких
these uh methods exist
этих ээ способов
and what are they called there, diplomatic
и как его называют там и дипломатических
and non-diplomatic and secrets and so on Well,
и не дипломатических и тайнах и проче Ну
okay, I don't understand Look,
хорошо я не не понимаю Вот смотри вот
now yours is coming, let's say, let's say, I will say
сейчас идёт твоя как вы хотите
this I
допустим вот я скажу такую вещь Я так
think that this, what is his name, your Zelensky,
думаю что этот как же его ваш Зеленский
he will not sign anything
он ничего подписывать не будет Не будет
Zelensky will not be there, they will simply remove him Okay Well, they will remove
Зеленского просто его уберут Хорошо Вот
him yes They will put in another one Like this
его уберут да Поставят другого Как этот
other one He will not be able to sign And the
другой Он не сможет подписать И
Verkhovna Rada What about the Verkhovna Rada, it
Верховную Раду Де что Верховная Рада она
must ratify this Yes Yes
же должна ратифицировать это Да Да
Another Verkhovna Rada Well, how else Well,
Другую Верховную Раду Ну как другую Ну
look how you will do it, you will
посмотри как как вы сделаете вы
put in another Verkhovna Rada they will
поставите другую Верховную Раду
buy Yeah The thing is that, look, you
купят Угу Дело в том что смотрите вы же
understand that any mood in Ukraine is
понимаете что любой настроения в Украине
such that anyone in Kyiv will say:
такие да что любой кто в Киеве скажет:
"I will sign that we are giving
"Я подпишу что мы отдаём россиянам
territories to the Russians" Yes, he will be swept away in one hour and
территории" Да его сметут за оди час и
will sit in Rostov Yes
будет в Ростове сидеть да
That is, in Russia, well, I don't see  I just do
То есть у России ну я не вижу просто я
n't see how Russia can achieve its goals except by capturing
не вижу как Россия кроме как захвата
Kyiv and putting its
Киева да и постав туда своего
puppet politician there. The
марионеточной полити как она может
question is
Вопрос
complicated. The question is false. I'm
сложный Вопрос ложный Я
inclined, I say again, I'm
склоняюсь я говор ещё раз говорю
inclined to think that
склоняюсь к тому что
they'll
э-э
buy, they'll just
купят просто
buy. Now look, this what's his name
купят Вот сейчас смотри ээ этот как его
Trump,
Трамп
yes, how much did they have there, I remember that
да сколько они там ээ я помню такая
figure was 5 billion to
цифра была 5 млрд на то чтобы
organize Maidan. I think it was someone
организовать Майдан Это по-моему кто-то
Nulon, I think there was a girl running around there, yeah,
Нулон по-моему такая там девица бегала
yeah, that's 5 billion. And now how much have they
да Угу Вот 5 млрд А сейчас сколько они
already poured into
вбухали уже в
Ukraine? And now they're saying: "Come on,
Украину А теперь говорят: "Ну-ка давай
guys, give me your money back." And what does
мужики назад деньги" А причём тут
Ukraine have to do with it? Look, I'm asking what you want.
Украина Смотри я спрашиваю как вы хотите
Not me. What do you mean by that? Set such
Не я я к чему что ээ поставить такие
conditions that it's just a friend. After all, it
условия что просто дру Ведь сейчас
turns out that now, for example, the same
получается что вот допустим тот же
agreement. To be honest, I've never seen it anywhere
договор я так честно говоря его нигде не
and I think you haven't seen it either. What kind of
видел и я думаю вы тоже не видели Что за
agreement is it on these rare earths? Have you read it?
договор по этим редкозёма Вы его читали
No, I haven't. Well, you've
Нет не читал Ну вы
seen it. You've seen this agreement.
видели Видели этот догово Ещё раз
Look again, I'm not saying that. Look, this is
смотрите я не в том я говорю смотри это
Ukraine, America, how?  you want to win I
Украина Америка как вы хотите победить Я
just can't That's how you Russians
просто не могу Вот как у вас россиян вы
say: "I support the war so that
говорите: "Я поддерживаю войну для того
if we don't achieve it we'll fall apart"
чтобы мы если не добьёмся мы распадёмся"
I believe you will fall apart How do you want to
Я верю вы распадётесь Как вы хотите
win How If we do
победить Как
n't wash it, then roll it over In short, you don't have an
Не мытём так катанием Короче нет у вас
image of victory Got it I don't have it I'm not
образа победы Понял У меня нет Я не
Thank God I'm not the president I understood what
Слава богу я не президент Понял то что
he did there And now you want me to
он там натворил А теперь вы хотите чтобы
scold him for it Well, you
я за него отчитал Ну так вы же
support it
поддерживаете
Cunningly like Okay Well, no, I'll tell you this
Хитро как О'кей Ну не ну я вам скажу
I'll still tell you this that -t
такую вещь Я вам всё-таки скажу такую
simply force Well,
-т просто вынудить
how yes You see, in order to force, the
ну как да Вы смотрите чтобы вынудить
concept of forcing is coercion by force
понятие вынудить - это принуждение силой
yes That is, military force, for example, when it is
да То есть военная сила например когда
not necessarily by force Not necessarily No
не обязательно силой Не обязательно Нет
When you see when in Czechoslovakia in
Когда смотрите когда в Чехословакии в
1968 the government
шестьдесят восьмом году правительство
decided, uh, to go for liberal reforms
решило ээ пойти на либеральные реформы
yes Russia The Soviet Union led tanks into
да Россия Советский Союз вёл танки в
Czechoslovakia in Prague yes you took the
Чехословакию в Прагу да вы это забрал
oak tree and brought it to Moscow yes you
дубчика и привезли его в Москву да
installed a puppet
поставили там марионеточное
government there and  everything was decided That was
правильчество и всё решили Вот это было
coercion yes tanks in Prague - that was
принуждение да танки в Праге - это было
coercion yes Budapest psyat that yes it
принуждение да Будапешт псят что да это
was on the fifth sixth yes it was coercion
было пя шестого да это было принуждение
Budapestm There I will say one thing that there
Будапешм Там я скажу такую вещь что вот
was a
разница была
big difference Budapest - that is there I will tell you a
большая Будапешт - это там я вам скажу
kind of rebellion because it
такой своего рода мятеж потому
began with a massacre that
что началось с резни которые
provoked well let's say a
спровоцировали ну будем говорить
counter-revolution As I understood in short In general, the
контрреволюцию Как короче понял В общем
Hungarian
э венгерские
nationalists committed a massacre and the Soviet
националисты сделали резню а советские
artillerymen
артиллеристы из гаубиц
fired at Budapest from howitzers Well you know you
обстреливали Будапешт Ну вы знаете вы
say there were Soviet artillerymen
говорите там советские артиллеристы
by the way no one fired from howitzers there
кстати с гаубис там никто не стрелял Там
Look, the artillerymen were pounding Budapest That's for
смотри артиллеристы лупашили Будапеш Это
sure If they fired then the tanks were
точно Если стреляли то танки
not the artillery was working Well no no no there
не артиллерия была работала Ну не ну ну
were no such big targets for this
не не было целей для этого таких больших
Now I will check directly I at
Сейчас я прямо проверю Я я во всяком
least have not heard I read about these military
случае не слышал Я читал про эти боевые
actions that were happening But in
действия что творилось Но а в
Czechoslovakia, that's when the
Чехословайки это вот как раз уже начался
crisis had just begun Yes by the way in Hungary when
кризис Да кстати и в Венгрии когда вот
that
это
began uh the
началось
crisis of this
э-э кризис вот этой идеологии
socialist ideology  or there was an
социалистической или вот был
artillery shelling of the city yes Budapest
артиллерийский обстрел города да Будапеш
was
было
Oh listen air strikes on
Ой слушайте авиа авиационные удары по
Budapest Well in short it was fun No it's also
Будапеш Ну короче весело был Нет то же
official here on the Internet there are a lot of
официально вот в интернете куча
materials you enter like this has been going on for a long time now
материалов вводишь типа это ж уже давно
excuse me but sometimes they write so much of
вот вы меня извините но столько иногда
everything you understand that I don't I don't know
всякой понимаете что я не я не знаю
what would have been the point of bombing when
какой смысл бы было бомбить когда туда
troops entered there I do
вошли войска
n't know Well okay you know proving uh
Не знаю Ну ладно знаете доказывать ээ
it's very difficult you understand It wasn't It was
это очень сложно понимаете Было не было
Here Let's end on a good note Let's
Вот Давайте закончим на хорошей ноте
let's pray for peace Are you a
Давай давайте помолимся за мир Вы
believer No I am a believer And can I pray I am a believer
верующий человек Нет я верующий И можно
but I am not a
я помолюсь Я верующий но я не
churchgoer I don't think I am just a
воцерклённый Я не считаю Я просто
believer Yes I think and someone should stand by the Almighty
верующий Да Я думаю и Всевышнем кто-то
Now I will pray for peace then
Сейчас я помолюсь за мир тогда
Yes God's right send us peace As the
Да божий правый пошли нам мир Как гласит
Bible says peace is not the absence of war it is the
Библия мир - это не отсутствие войны это
absence of Moscow Amen
отсутствие Москвы Аминь
Vedoma phrase Korchinskaya N of course
Ведома фраза Корчинская Н конечно
handsome Like subscription comment Remember
красавчик Лайк подписка коммент Помните
peace is not the absence of war Peace is the
мир - это не отсутствие войны Мир - это
absence of Moscow Grandfather understands everything correctly
отсутствие Москвы Дед всё правильно
Russia has a huge
понимает Россия имеет огромнейший
potential for disintegration has huge
потенциал к распаду имеет огромнейшие
problems  national regional
проблемы национальные региональные
interethnic interfaith
межеэтнические межконфессиональные да
and failure to achieve the goals of the SVO in Ukraine
и недостижение целей СВО на Украине по
due to the defeat of the Russian Federation will
факту поражения Российской Федерации
very quickly lead to the collapse of the
приведёт очень быстро к распаду
Russian Federation, which is what they are afraid of
Российской Федерации что они и боятся
Glory to Ukraine
Слава Украине
Subscribe to my Instagram I don't know why
Підпишись на мій Instagram Я не знаю для
you are here, why else should I
чго це тобі для чого ще тобі там
watch you on Face But for you it's one or
дивитись на Face Але для тебе це оди або
three
три
clicks, you support me and I will say:
клика підтримаєш мене и я буду казати:
"Wow, I have a bunch of followers and I
"Вау в мене там купа фоловерів и в мене
will be in a great
буде класний
mood, cool Subscribe to my Instagram,
настро круті Підпишись на мій Instagram
Pope Andrey"
попик Андрей"
So, let me wait for you
Отак Давай я тебя чекаю